<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: App | Gadget Habit]]></title>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/categories/app/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-05T10:32:22-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://michaelevans.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Evans]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Newest App: Bike Finder]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/09/16/my-newest-app-bike-finder/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T23:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/09/16/my-newest-app-bike-finder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/2013/09/16/map.png" width="240" height="400" title="Map" ></p>

<p>Last week I released my newest Android app, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.michaelevans.bikefinder&amp;referrer=utm_source%3Dblog">Bike Finder</a>. It&rsquo;s a fairly straight forward application that allows you to find bikes and stations for use with Washington DC&rsquo;s Capital Bikeshare system. For those of you not local to DC, Capital Bikeshare is a system that lets you use bikes that are available at docking stations all over the city, as well as parts of northern Virginia. The app is free, and I&rsquo;m looking into adding additional cities that have companies that make their bike sharing data available (currently investigating New York City, Montreal and the Bay Area). If you&rsquo;d like to get your city added, <a href="http://twitter.com/m_evans10">let me know</a>, and I&rsquo;ll see if the data is available, and add it to the to-do list.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/2013/09/16/details.png" width="240" height="400" title="Details" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also planning to add some other cool features, like a notification when a &ldquo;favorite&rdquo; station is low on bikes, or when a &ldquo;favorite&rdquo; station is full (so you know you&rsquo;ll have to bring the bike elsewhere). I&rsquo;m also looking into adding some directions/searching feature, so you can navigate your way around the city without having to leave the application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
