<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Chromebook | Gadget Habit]]></title>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/categories/chromebook/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-14T23:55:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://michaelevans.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Evans]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Crouton on a Chromebook Pixel]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/06/11/running-crouton-on-a-chromebook-pixel/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T21:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/06/11/running-crouton-on-a-chromebook-pixel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So a few weeks back at Google IO, Google handed out an awesome laptop to attendees, the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/devices/details?id=chromebook_pixel_wifi">Chromebook Pixel</a>. For those who aren&rsquo;t familiar with it, the Pixel is a laptop running Google&rsquo;s ChromeOS, with the highest resolution screen available on a laptop (2560x1700). Unfortunately for me (and owners of the other Chromebooks), there&rsquo;s a few things you can&rsquo;t do in Chrome, like writing software in the new Android Studio!</p>

<p>In order to work around this limitation in ChromeOS, a developer at Google named David Schneider developed a set of scripts called <a href="https://github.com/dnschneid/crouton">crouton</a>. Crouton allows you to run Ubuntu inside a your ChromeOS system, so that you can easily swap back and forth between the operating systems. This is not limited to the Pixel, so if you&rsquo;re using another model Chromebook, even dating back to the CR-48, this guide should work for you.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Installing Crouton</h3>

<h4>Step One: Enable Developer Mode (This might vary slightly depending on your model)</h4>

<p><em>Warning: Switching into or out of developer mode will wipe all the user data on the ChromeOS machine.</em></p>

<ol>
<li>Shutdown your machine.</li>
<li>Press and hold esc + refresh, and push the power button to turn on your computer.</li>
<li>Push Ctrl+D to be prompted to enable developer mode.</li>
<li>Hit enter, and watch the progress bar at the top of the screen as the system is wiped.</li>
<li>When the machine boots up again, either wait til it boots, or you can hit Ctrl+D again to start faster.</li>
</ol>


<h4>Step Two: Install Crouton</h4>

<ol>
<li>Download crouton <a href="http://goo.gl/fd3zc">here</a>.</li>
<li>Open a shell (Ctrl+Alt+T, type shell and hit enter) and run <code>sudo sh -e ~/Downloads/crouton -t xfce,touch</code>.</li>
<li>Go get a drink, come back and answer some questions.</li>
<li>Done! Start up an XFCE session with <code>sudo startxfce4</code>.</li>
</ol>


<h4>Step Three: Enjoy Ubuntu on your Chromebook!</h4>

<p>To switch back and forth between ChromeOS and Crouton, swap with Ctrl+Alt+Back and the sequence Ctrl+Alt+Forward followed by Ctrl+Alt+Refresh.</p>

<p>Pro tip: Increase the font size under the display settings, so that the text is a little more readable!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
