<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Google | Gadget Habit]]></title>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/categories/google/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-14T23:59:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://michaelevans.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Evans]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google IO 2013 and Google Reader]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/03/14/google-io-2013-and-google-reader/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T23:52:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/03/14/google-io-2013-and-google-reader</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday was a bittersweet day for me in the world of Google. On the bright side, I was one of the lucky few to acquire a ticket to Google IO 2013. This will be my third Google IO, and I cannot be more excited to attend this year. The first year I went brought about the introduction to Android 3.1 (Honeycomb), which began the improvments for Android's Holo Theme, as well as layouts for tablets. Last year was even more groundbreaking, with the unveiling of a <a href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2012/06/26/shots-from-outside-io-2012/">few</a> new <a href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2012/09/07/nexus-q-review/">Nexus</a> <a href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2012/07/03/nexus-7-review/">devices</a>, Android 4.1 (Jelly Bean), as well as <a href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/02/20/googles-project-glass/">Project Glass</a>. I can't even imagine what they will have in store for us this year.</p>

<p>Here comes the bad news though: <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2013/03/a-second-spring-of-cleaning.html">Google Reader is being shut down</a>. If you don't know, Google Reader is an RSS reader for the web, a hub for all your subscriptions online. This pending shutdown has caused quite a stir, leading to many users scrambling to <a href="http://www.newsblur.com/">new</a> <a href="http://www.feedly.com/">RSS</a> readers, or <a href="http://blog.digg.com/post/45355701332/were-building-a-reader">building new ones</a>. (There was even a <a href="http://mashable.com/2013/03/14/white-house-google-reader/">petition on whitehouse.org</a> for the government to intervene…)</p>

<p>Google Reader was one of my favorite Google applications, so it's quite sad to see it go. Hopefully one of these replacements will provide a good enough experience so the switch is a bit less painful.</p>

<hr />

<p>Suggestions for a new RSS reader? Predictions for IO 2013? Drop me a line on <a href="https://twitter.com/m_evans10">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://plus.google.com/114052868601022948953/posts">Google Plus</a>, or leave a comment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guide to Google Authorship]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/02/25/guide-to-google-authorship/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-25T21:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/02/25/guide-to-google-authorship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I noticed something interesting about my blog: I'm now a verified author! What does that mean, you might ask? When one of the pages of my blog shows up in a Google search, it will look a little something like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/02/25/authorship.png" width="600" height="400" title="Google Authorship" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Why might you want Google Authorship?</p>

<ul>
<li>It helps distinguish your content from other search results.</li>
<li>You might get more followers on Google+.</li>
</ul>


<p>Would you like to get Authorship on Google? It's actually extremely easy. Just follow the following steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>You need a Google+ profile with a profile picture of yourself.</li>
<li>On the profile editor of Google+, there is a "Contributor to" section; add your website here.</li>
<li>Add a link like this: <code>&lt;a href="[your profile URL]?rel=author"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;</code> somewhere on your website.</li>
<li>You're done! You can validate what your site would look like as a search result with a tool found <a href="http://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/richsnippets">here</a>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Keep in mind that Google doesn't <em>guarantee</em> to show author information in Google Web Search or Google News results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google's Project Glass]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/02/20/googles-project-glass/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-20T20:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/02/20/googles-project-glass</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This morning Google put up some new details regarding Project Glass, including <a href="http://www.google.com/glass/start/how-it-feels/">a video</a> showing what it's like to wear Glass, and a <a href="http://www.google.com/glass/start/what-it-does/">list of things</a> that Glass can do. They are also sponsoring a new contest where anyone can <a href="http://www.google.com/glass/start/how-to-get-one/">join the Glass Explorers</a> (people who will be getting the Developer Edition). I was fortunate enough to be able to attend the Glass Foundry event in New York earlier this month, and got to experience Project Glass first hand. While I cannot say too much more than what you can gather from the Google page, I do have some exciting news!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>Me (and my team, which included Jacob Hilker and Ryan Warner), won the Glass Foundry Hackathon! Like I said, I cannot share much more about it, but I do have this sweet picture of me wearing them:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/02/20/glass.jpg" width="400" height="400" title="Project Glass" ></p>

<p>And the best part is the prize for the winners - a free Glass Explorer device (when they are available, of course).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shots from outside Google IO 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2012/06/26/shots-from-outside-io-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-26T09:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2012/06/26/shots-from-outside-io-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm in San Francisco for <a href="https://developers.google.com/events/io/">Google IO 2012</a>, and while Nate and I were wandering the city, we passed by the Moscone Center and I snapped a couple of photos.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012/06/26/window.JPG" width="700" height="200" title="Giant Google Banner" ></p>

<p>My guess is that there will be a Nexus tablet (see the Nexus banner on the third floor), with NFC and Google Wallet, and then attendees will get to test the tap-to-pay out at the Google Wallet sponsored Google Store.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012/06/26/nexus.JPG" width="700" height="200" title="Nexus Banner" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/2012/06/26/wallet.JPG" width="700" height="200" title="Google Store" ></p>

<p>We'll certainly find out tomorrow though!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
